<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <info>
        <title>Getting Started with Ncqrs</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Pieter Joost</firstname><surname>van de
                Sande</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>not yet</pubdate>
    </info>
    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>This reference documentation explains what the Ncqrs framework is, how it can help and
            how you can use it.</para>
        <section>
            <title>What is Ncqrs?</title>
            <para>Ncqrs is a framework for .NET that helps build scalable, extensible and
                maintainable applications by supporting developers apply the Command Query
                Responsibility Segregation (CQRS) architectural pattern. It does so by providing an
                infrastructure and implementations for the most important building blocks for
                command handling and execution, domain modeling, event sourcing, domain events,
                denormalization and event storage. These building blocks help you to focus on the
                code that adds business value. They come with annotation, convention and
                configuration support and help you to write isolated and testable code.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>When to use Ncqrs</title>
            <para>cotty said in Star Trek V: <emphasis>“How many times do I have to tell you, the
                    right tool for the right job!“</emphasis>. Ncqrs isn’t the right tool for every
                job. Which means that not every application will benefit from Ncqrs. Simple <link
                    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Create,_read,_update_and_delete"
                    >CRUD</link> based systems without much behavior will not benefit from it. But
                there is a wide variety of applications that do benefit from Ncqrs.</para>
            <para>Applications will most likely benefit from Ncqrs when they have one or more of the
                following characteristics:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Long life time</emphasis> The project will exists
                        for a longer period or time and therefore has the needs to organically
                        grow.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Need to be scalable</emphasis> The application needs
                        the be scalable when needed.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Contain business logic</emphasis> The application
                        contains business logic that needs to stay maintainable.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Demand for integration</emphasis>Other applications
                        need to be able to integrate with it.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Having multiple views</emphasis> There are multiple
                        screens, reports or application that have there own view on the data.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Must have a audit log </emphasis> All state changes
                        must be logged and a auditable log needs to be build.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>System requirements</title>
            <para> You need the .NET Framework 3.5 or higher to use the Ncqrs framework. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>License information</title>
            <para>The Ncqrs framework and its documentation are licensed under the Apache License,
                Version 2.0 (the “License”); you may not use this file except in compliance with the
                License. You may obtain a copy of the License at <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"/>.</para>
            <para>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed
                under the License is distributed on an “AS IS” BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR
                CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
                language governing permissions and limitations under the License.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Contribution</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Ncqrs is an open source project that is driven by software developers that love to
                make the world just a little bit better. The project is driven by the contribution
                of people. Whether it is that they give feedback, make a bug report, fixing some
                code or add some documentation. The project would not be a success without the
                people that are contributing. It keeps the project vibrant, alive and on the path of
                progress.</para>
            <para>Active constribution, an contribution period longer then 3 months, is rewarded
                with licenses of the following products: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>ReSharper</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NDepend</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>OxygenXML</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>Please consider contribution in one or more ways as described in this
                chapter.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Feedback</title>
            <para>One of the key drivers for us is feedback. We take all feedback serious and it
                help us in the decisions we make and to choose the parts where we spent our time on.
                It can also be good to just put a smile on our face. Whether you just want to say
                that we rock, that you would like to see feature X or Y, or that you are confused
                about something related to the project. You can drop your feedback through one of
                the follow way:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/ncqrs">@ncqrs at
                        twitter</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="mailto:feedback@ncqrs.org">Feedback mail</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="http://groups.google.com/group/ncqrs-dev">Ncqrs-dev
                            discussion group at google</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Documentation</title>
            <para>A solid framework is one thing, but a framework is almost worthless without
                documentation. Applications that are build using the Ncqrs framework will have it as
                part of there fundament. A choice for a component can have a big impact in the
                future. Documentation is important to guide people and preventing them from making
                mistakes. This documentation can come in many ways. For example, the current form
                that you are reading. But also quick starts, blog posts, how to video’s, they all
                have a big impact. Did you blogged about your experience, did you find a weak spot
                in our documentation or do you have any other contribution, please let us
                know!</para>
            <para>This documentation is stored in the main repository of the framework, so you can
                fork it, make a change and do a pull request.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>The architecture</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Change is a fact of life in software development. Knowledge moves forward, new
                insights are obtained and so requirements change. This makes it important to develop
                applications that can deal with this fact. A well known way to solve this problem is
                to split a system apart in layers. This architecture is known as N-tier. In this
                architecture the system is horizontal split into logical layers that depend on each
                other like a stack of plates. An layer only depends on the layer below. Layers never
                depend on a layer above, or further down then the direct layer below. This is a
                great way to reach a certain level of abstraction. It also gives the ability to
                replace a implementation without breaking a lot. You only break the contract with
                the layer that depends on the layer that gets replaced, and that is always zero for
                the top layer and only one for all others. </para>
            <para>Although N-tier has been the standard for years, it also comes with a price.
                Layers hides a lot of power and details. They can only use the power of a layer
                directly below, never on a layer below that one. It also does not allow you to
                optimize layers for a certain concern other then broad ones like User Interface,
                Business and Data Access. For example, the User Interface uses Objects from the
                Business tier but can never query the data directly from the database.</para>
            <para>Ncqrs helps developers apply the Command Query Responsibility Segregation (CQRS)
                architectural pattern. This pattern itself is quite simple. It states that the
                component that processes commands should be separated from the one that processes
                queries.</para>
            <para>Instead of separating the system in horizontal layers, as we know from N-tier
                architectures, we separate them also vertically. This means, instead of defining
                layers for user interface, business logic and data storage, we split by commands and
                queries.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The big picture</title>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="architecture-overview" xreflabel="">
                    <title>Architecture overview</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/architecture-overview.png" width=""/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para linkend="system-flow">The figure <xref linkend="architecture-overview"/> shows the
                architectural overview of a CQRS based system. The first thing you should notice is
                that it is not just horizontally layered as you might know from general
                architectures. In it's fundament it is separated by a read- and a write side. This
                means that the user interface - or any other top component - doesn't use the same
                model to read data as to write data. Instead of getting for example customer data,
                modifying it and save the changes, the user interface read all the data needed from
                a read database, displays it to the user and to make modification it sends command
                to the command handlers. These command handlers make changes to the domain. The
                changes in the domain cause events to occur, these events represent the changes.
                These events are stored and published to denormalizers. The denormalizers make
                modifications to the read database according to the events and event data. Via this
                way the read databases are kept up to date. Now the user interface can read the data
                again and we have a close loop. This process is illustrated in <xref
                    linkend="system-flow"/>.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="system-flow">
                    <title>System flow</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/system_flow.png" width=""/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Components</title>
        <section>
            <title>Command handlers</title>
            <para>The user interface sends commands to make changes to the system. Commands are
                simple object that contain all the data needed to perform the underlying action. An
                example of the command could be <code>MoveUserToNewAddress</code>. The command
                should hold the new address for the user and the user id that indicates which user
                has moved.</para>
            <para>Commands also tent to express intent by there name. For example, although the
                command <code>MoveUserToNewAddress</code> and <code>CorrectAddressForUser</code>
                both contain the same data – the address and the user id – the intent is definitely
                different. All commands are send to a Command Service. This service receives the
                commands and routes them to the corresponding command executors. All command
                executors respond to a specific command and execute an action based on there
                content. Command executors should not contain any business logic. The only thing
                they do is making changes to aggregate roots from the domain and makes changes to
                them. To stay away from plumbing code, Ncqrs supports mapping for command to map a
                command directly to an domain object.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Domain</title>
            <para>Command executors make changes to aggregate roots in the domain. All business
                logic is captured within these objects and is not used for querying. This allows us
                to optimize this model for behavior. Aggregate roots contain the actual business
                logic and are responsible for guarding their own invariants. State changes on
                aggregate roots cause domain events to occur. This sequence of domain events
                represents all the changes that has been made. This pattern is called event
                sourcing.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Events</title>
            <para>All state changes in the domain are represented by domain events. They are simple
                object that contain all data related to the change. We gave two examples of command
                names. The events that are related to the state change of these commands will be
                    <code>UserMovedToNewAddress</code> and <code>AddressCorrectedForUser</code>.
                Notice that the names are in the past tense.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Repository</title>
            <para>The repository is used to get and save aggregate roots. This is done by there
                events. Saving an aggregate root will result in persisting all his uncommitted
                events that occurred while making change to it. Getting an aggregate root is done by
                getting this events and replaying them to build up the aggregate root into the
                latest state. The events are stored in the event store and when an aggregate root is
                saved, all the events will also be published to the event store.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Event Store</title>
            <para>All events that have occurred end up in the event store. It contains all the event
                that represents the state changes in the system. These can be used to build up the
                current state by replaying them all. This store can also be used to fill up new or
                repair existing read model.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Event Bus</title>
            <para>When an aggregate root is saved via the repository all the uncommitted events that
                represent the state changes that has been made are persisted into the event store.
                Beside that, the repository also publish these events via the event bus. This bus
                publishes it to everybody that has registered itself as one being interested in the
                events. An event bus can be synchronous or asynchronous, but the read models will be
                consistent at some point of time.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Denormalizers</title>
            <para>There are different event handlers subscribed to the events bus. The most common
                one are denormalizers. These event handlers take events and makes changes to the
                read model based on them. For example, a denormalizer could update the users address
                in the user table based on the data in the <code>UserMovedToNewAddress</code> event.
                But it could also update the total number of users in city <emphasis role="italic"
                    >X</emphasis> based on that the same event. </para>
            <para>Event handlers are not only interesting to keep the read model up to date. But
                they could also be written to make changes to an external system or send warning
                email to the business when certain event occur. It could also be that an event
                handler issues a new command. Event handlers are great components to extent the
                system with new functionality without making changes in it.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Read Model</title>
            <para>An important part of every application is data. Most of the screen in an user
                interface request it. But every screen just tents to have a different view on the
                data. For example, one wants all the products with there name, price and category,
                while another wants the products with there name and top 3 latest product review
                score and name of the reviewer. Read models are models that can be optimized for
                data querying. And what is a optimal query? That is a query that just queries the
                data from one source. In other words: select * from x where y. No joining, just give
                me the data. We can accomplish this by creating one table per view. So that every
                view can just request data by a simple query. You read model doesn’t even have to be
                a relational database, it could be a document based database that contains a
                collection for every view. Ncqrs does only provide a base class for denormalizers
                that allows them be subscribed to the event bus. The denormalization itself is
                simple and straightforward.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Aggregate Root</title>
        <section>
            <title>How they work</title>
            <section>
                <para>The base for an aggregate root is the <code>AggregateRoot</code> class. It is
                    located in the <code>Ncqrs.Domain</code> namespace. There are also base classes
                    that add mapping support.<figure>
                        <title>Making changes to an aggregate root <footnote>
                                <para>See the full sequence diagram here: <link
                                        xlink:href="http://www.websequencediagrams.com/?lz=VXNlciBDb2RlLT5BZ2dyZWdhdGUgUm9vdDogbmV3KGJheikKAAsOLT5OZXdGb29CYXJDcmVhdGVkRXZlbgAUHABJEEFwcGx5ADAFKGV2bnQADyJPbk5ld0FnZ1Jvb3QAbQcAMwcAgSQbRm9vKGJhcgCBLRJGb28AgSUNABATAG9DAF4IAIFdBg&amp;s=rose"
                                        >websequencediagrams.com</link>.</para>
                            </footnote></title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/agg-root-sequence.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure></para>
                <section>
                    <title>Mapped by convention</title>
                    <para>Since aggregate roots modify there own state by handling events, you can
                        end up with a lot of event handlers. To prevent you from writing a lot of
                        plumbing code to wire event handlers the Ncqrs framework offers aggregate
                        root based types that support event handler mapping.</para>
                    <para>When you use the <code>AggregateRootMappedByConvention</code> class as
                        base for your aggregate roots you are able to create event handlers very
                        easily by convention. Here is an example of an event handling method in the
                        aggregate
                        root:<programlisting><code>protected void OnFooEvent(FooEvent e)
{
	// Will be mapped as a event handler for the FooEvent.
}</code></programlisting></para>
                    <para>All methods that satisfy the following convention are mapped as event
                        handler:</para>
                    <para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Method is an instance method (not static).</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Method name starts with <emphasis role="italic"
                                            ><code>On</code></emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
                                            ><code>on</code></emphasis>. Like:
                                        <code>OnProductAdded</code> or
                                    <code>onProductAdded</code>.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The method accepts only one parameter.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>That parameter is type of, or inherit from, the
                                        <code>SourcedEvent</code> class.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Is not marked with the <code>NoEventHandlerAttribute</code>
                                    attribute.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                    <para>Although a method may be public, protected, internal, protected internal
                        or private and can be virtual we do not advice you to make event handlers
                        public.</para>
                    <section>
                        <title>Excluding methods</title>
                        <para>Sometimes you want to prevent methods that satisfy the convention for
                            being mapped. The can be excluded from the mapping by annotating them
                            with the <code>NoEventHandlerAttribute</code> attribute. All methods
                            annotated with this attribute will be ignored in the mapping process.
                            The following code shows a method that will be excluded:</para>
                        <programlisting><code>[NoEventHandler]
protected void OnFooEvent(FooEvent e)
{
    // Will not be mapped.
}</code></programlisting>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
